who die before the age of five every year. And what you find is really a phenomenal success story which is not widely known, that we are making incredible progress. We go from 20 million not long after I was born to now we're down to about six million. So this is a story largely of vaccines. Smallpox was killing a couple million kids a year. That was eradicated, so that got down to zero. Measles was killing a couple million a year. That's down to a few hundred thousand. Anyway, this is a chart where you want to get that number to continue, and it's going to be possible, using the science of new vaccines, getting the vaccines out to kids. We can actually accelerate the progress. The last decade, that number has dropped faster than ever in history, and so I just love the fact that you can say, okay, if we can invent new vaccines, we can get them out there, use the very latest understanding of these things, and get the delivery right, that we can perform a miracle. CA: I mean, you do the math on this, and it works out, I think, literally to thousands of kids' lives saved every day compared to the prior year. It's not reported. An airliner with 200-plus deaths is a far, far bigger story than that. Does that drive you crazy? BG: Yeah, because it's a silent thing going on. It's a kid, one kid at a time. Ninety-eight percent of this has nothing to do with natural disasters, and yet, people's charity, when they see a natural disaster, are wonderful. It's incredible how people think, okay, that could be me, and the money flows. These causes have been a bit invisible. Now that the Millennium Development Goals and various things are getting out there, we are seeing some increased generosity, so the goal is to get this well below a million, which should be possible in our lifetime. CA: Maybe it needed someone who is turned on by numbers and graphs rather than just the big, sad face to get engaged. I mean, you've used it in your letter this year, you used basically this argument to say that aid, contrary to the current meme that aid is kind of worthless and broken, that actually it has been effective. BG: Yeah, well people can take, there is some aid that was well-meaning and didn't go well. There's some venture capital investments that were well-meaning and didn't go well. You shouldn't just say, okay, because of that, because we don't have a perfect record, this is a bad endeavor. You should look at, what was your goal? How are you trying to uplift nutrition and survival and literacy so these countries can take care of themselves, and say wow, this is going well, and be smarter. We can spend aid smarter. It is not all a panacea. We can do better than venture capital, I think, including big hits like this. CA: Traditional wisdom is that it's pretty hard for married couples to work together. How have you guys managed it? MG: Yeah, I've had a lot of women say to me, "I really don't think I could work with my husband. That just wouldn't work out." You know, we enjoy it, and we don't -- this foundation has been a coming to for both of us in its continuous learning journey, and we don't travel together as much for the foundation, actually, as we used to when Bill was working at Microsoft. We have more trips where we're traveling separately, but I always know when I come home, Bill's going to be interested in what I learned, whether it's about women or girls or something new about the vaccine delivery chain, or this person that is a great leader. He's going to listen and be really interested. And he knows when he comes home, even if it's to talk about the speech he did or the data or what he's learned, I'm really interested, and I think we have a really collaborative relationship. But we don't every minute together, that's for sure. (Laughter) CA: But now you are, and we're very happy that you are. Melinda, early on, you were basically largely running the show. Six years ago, I guess, Bill came on full time, so moved from Microsoft and became full time. That must have been hard, adjusting to that. No? MG: Yeah. I think actually, for the foundation employees, there was way more angst for them than there was for me about Bill coming. I was actually really excited. I mean, Bill made this decision even obviously before it got announced in 2006, and it was really his decision, but again, it was a beach vacation where we were walking on the beach and he was starting to think of this idea. And for me, the excitement of Bill putting his brain and his heart against these huge global problems, these inequities, to me that was exciting. Yes, the foundation employees had angst about that. (Applause) CA: That's cool. MG: But that went away within three months, once he was there. BG: Including some of the employees. MG: That's what I said, the employees, it went away for them three months after you were there. BG: No, I'm kidding. MG: Oh, you mean, the employees didn't go away. BG: A few of them did, but — (Laughter) CA: So what do you guys argue about? Sunday, 11 o'clock, you're away from work, what comes up? What's the argument? BG: Because we built this thing together from the beginning, it's this great partnership. I had that with Paul Allen in the early days of Microsoft. I had it with Steve Ballmer as Microsoft got bigger, and now Melinda, and in even stronger, equal ways, is the partner, so we talk a lot about which things should we give more to, which groups are working well? She's got a lot of insight. She'll sit down with the employees a lot. We'll take the different trips she described. So there's a lot of collaboration. I can't think of anything where one of us had a super strong opinion about one thing or another? CA: How about you, Melinda, though? Can you? (Laughter) You never know. MG: Well, here's the thing. We come at things from different angles, and I actually think that's really good. So Bill can look at the big data and say, "I want to act based on these global statistics." For me, I come at it from intuition. I meet with lots of people on the ground and Bill's taught me to take that and read up to the global data and see if they match, and I think what I've taught him is to take that data and meet with people on the ground to understand, can you actually deliver that vaccine? Can you get a woman to accept those polio drops in her child's mouth? Because the delivery piece is every bit as important as the science. So I think it's been more a coming to over time towards each other's point of view, and quite frankly, the work is better because of it. CA: So, in vaccines and polio and so forth, you've had some amazing successes. What about failure, though? Can you talk about a failure and maybe what you've learned from it? BG: Yeah. Fortunately, we can afford a few failures, because we've certainly had them. We do a lot of drug work or vaccine work that you know you're going to have different failures. Like, we put out, one that got a lot of publicity was asking for a better condom. Well, we got hundreds of ideas. Maybe a few of those will work out. We were very naïve, certainly I was, about a drug for a disease in India, visceral leishmaniasis, that I thought, once I got this drug, we can just go wipe out the disease. Well, turns out it took an injection every day for 10 days. It took three more years to get it than we expected, and then there was no way it was going to get out there. Fortunately, we found out that if you go kill the sand flies, you probably can have success there, but we spent five years, you could say wasted five years, and about 60 million, on a path that turned out to have very modest benefit when we got there. CA: You're spending, like, a billion dollars a year in education, I think, something like that. Is anything, the story of what's gone right there is quite a long and complex one. Are there any failures that you can talk about? MG: Well, I would say a huge lesson for us out of the early work is we thought that these small schools were the answer, and small schools definitely help. They bring down the dropout rate. They have less violence and crime in those schools. But the thing that we learned from that work, and what turned out to be the fundamental key, is a great teacher in front of the classroom. If you don't have an effective teacher in the front of the classroom, I don't care how big or small the building is, you're not going to change the trajectory of whether that student will be ready for college. (Applause) CA: So Melinda, this is you and your eldest daughter, Jenn. And just taken about three weeks ago, I think, three or four weeks ago. Where was this? MG: So we went to Tanzania. Jenn's been to Tanzania. All our kids have been to Africa quite a bit, actually. And we did something very different, which is, we decided to go spend two nights and three days with a family. Anna and Sanare are the parents. They invited us to come and stay in their boma. Actually, the goats had been there, I think, living in that particular little hut on their little compound before we got there. And we stayed with their family, and we really, really learned what life is like in rural Tanzania. And the difference between just going and visiting for half a day or three quarters of a day versus staying overnight was profound, and so let me just give you one explanation of that. They had six children, and as I talked to Anna in the kitchen, we cooked for about five hours in the cooking hut that day, and as I talked to her, she had absolutely planned and spaced with her husband the births of their children. It was a very loving relationship. This was a Maasai warrior and his wife, but they had decided to get married, they clearly had respect and love in the relationship. Their children, their six children, the two in the middle were twins, 13, a boy, and a girl named Grace. And when we'd go out to chop wood and do all the things that Grace and her mother would do, Grace was not a child, she was an adolescent, but she wasn't an adult. She was very, very shy. So she kept wanting to talk to me and Jenn. We kept trying to engage her, but she was shy. And at night, though, when all the lights went out in rural Tanzania, and there was no moon that night, the first night, and no stars, and Jenn came out of our hut with her REI little headlamp on, Grace went immediately, and got the translator, came straight up to my Jenn and said, "When you go home, can I have your headlamp so I can study at night?" CA: Oh, wow. MG: And her dad had told me how afraid he was that unlike the son, who had passed his secondary exams, because of her chores, she'd not done so well and wasn't in the government school yet. He said, "I don't know how I'm going to pay for her education. I can't pay for private school, and she may end up on this farm like my wife." So they know the difference that an education can make in a huge, profound way. CA: I mean, this is another pic of your other two kids, Rory and Phoebe, along with Paul Farmer. Bringing up three children when you're the world's richest family seems like a social experiment without much prior art. How have you managed it? What's been your approach? BG: Well, I'd say overall the kids get a great education, but you've got to make sure they have a sense of their own ability and what they're going to go and do, and our philosophy has been to be very clear with them -- most of the money's going to the foundation -- and help them find something they're excited about. We want to strike a balance where they have the freedom to do anything but not a lot of money showered on them so they could go out and do nothing. And so far, they're fairly diligent, excited to pick their own direction. CA: You've obviously guarded their privacy carefully for obvious reasons. I'm curious why you've given me permission to show this picture now here at TED. MG: Well, it's interesting. As they get older, they so know that our family belief is about responsibility, that we are in an unbelievable situation just to live in the United States and have a great education, and we have a responsibility to give back to the world. And so as they get older and we are teaching them -- they have been to so many countries around the world — they're saying, we do want people to know that we believe in what you're doing, Mom and Dad, and it is okay to show us more. So we have their permission to show this picture, and I think Paul Farmer is probably going to put it eventually in some of his work. But they really care deeply about the mission of the foundation, too. CA: You've easily got enough money despite your vast contributions to the foundation to make them all billionaires. Is that your plan for them? BG: Nope. No. They won't have anything like that. They need to have a sense that their own work is meaningful and important. We read an article long, actually, before we got married, where Warren Buffett talked about that, and we're quite convinced that it wasn't a favor either to society or to the kids. CA: Well, speaking of Warren Buffett, something really amazing happened in 2006, when somehow your only real rival for richest person in America suddenly turned around and agreed to give 80 percent of his fortune to your foundation. How on Earth did that happen? I guess there's a long version and a short version of that. We've got time for the short version. BG: All right. Well, Warren was a close friend, and he was going to have his wife Suzie give it all away. Tragically, she passed away before he did, and he's big on delegation, and — (Laughter) — he said — CA: Tweet that. BG: If he's got somebody who is doing something well, and is willing to do it at no charge, maybe that's okay. But we were stunned. MG: Totally stunned. BG: We had never expected it, and it has been unbelievable. It's allowed us to increase our ambition in what the foundation can do quite dramatically. Half the resources we have come from Warren's mind-blowing generosity. CA: And I think you've pledged that by the time you're done, more than, or 95 percent of your wealth, will be given to the foundation. BG: Yes. CA: And since this relationship, it's amazing— (Applause) And recently, you and Warren have been going around trying to persuade other billionaires and successful people to pledge to give, what, more than half of their assets for philanthropy. How is that going? BG: Well, we've got about 120 people who have now taken this giving pledge. The thing that's great is that we get together yearly and talk about, okay, do you hire staff, what do you give to them? We're not trying to homogenize it. I mean, the beauty of philanthropy is this mind-blowing diversity. People give to some things. We look and go, "Wow." But that's great. That's the role of philanthropy is to pick different approaches, including even in one space, like education. We need more experimentation. But it's been wonderful, meeting those people, sharing their journey to philanthropy, how they involve their kids, where they're doing it differently, and it's been way more successful than we expected. Now it looks like it'll just keep growing in size in the years ahead. MG: And having people see that other people are making change with philanthropy, I mean, these are people who have created their own businesses, put their own ingenuity behind incredible ideas. If they put their ideas and their brain behind philanthropy, they can change the world. And they start to see others doing it, and saying, "Wow, I want to do that with my own money." To me, that's the piece that's incredible. CA: It seems to me, it's actually really hard for some people to figure out even how to remotely spend that much money on something else. There are probably some billionaires in the room and certainly some successful people. I'm curious, can you make the pitch? What's the pitch? BG: Well, it's the most fulfilling thing we've ever done, and you can't take it with you, and if it's not good for your kids, let's get together and brainstorm about what we can be done.
que mueren cada año antes de cumplir 5 años. Y encontramos una historia de éxito fenomenal, que no es muy conocida, de un avance increíble. Pasamos de 20 millones no mucho después de mi nacimiento a estar ahora por debajo de los 6 millones. Así que esta es una historia principalmente de vacunas. La viruela mataba a un par de millones de niños al año. Fue erradicada, así que bajó a cero. El sarampión mataba un par de millones al año. Ha bajado a unos pocos cientos de miles. Como sea, esta es una gráfica donde se quiere conseguir que esa cifra continúe, y será posible, mediante la ciencia de nuevas vacunas, produciendo las vacunas para los niños. De hecho podemos acelerar el progreso. En la última década, esa cifra ha bajado más rápido que nunca antes en la historia, y por eso me encanta decir está bien, si podemos inventar nuevas vacunas podemos sacarlos de allí, usar la explicación más moderna y hacer el reparto correcto, para poder hacer un milagro. CA: Hacen los cálculos, y funciona, literalmente, para salvar miles de vidas de niños cada año en comparación con el año anterior. No se informa. Un avión de pasajeros con más de 200 muertes es una historia mucho más importante que esa. ¿Eso los vuelve locos? BG: Sí, porque es algo que ocurre en silencio. Es un niño, un niño a la vez. El 98 % de esto no tiene nada que ver con desastres naturales y, sin embargo, la ayuda de la gente, cuando ven un desastre natural, es asombrosa. Es increíble cómo la gente piensa, "Ese podría ser yo", y el dinero fluye. Estas causas han sido un poco invisibles. Ahora que se conocen los Objetivos de Desarrollo del Milenio y se conocen varias cosas, estamos viendo una mayor generosidad, así que la meta es llegar a muy por debajo del millón, lo cual debería ser posible durante nuestra vida. CA: Tal vez se necesitaba a alguien conmovido por números y gráficos en lugar de solo la cara grande y triste, para comprometerse. Usaste eso en tu carta este año, usaste básicamente este argumento para decir que ayudar, contrario a la idea actual de que la ayuda es algo sin valor, que no funciona, de hecho ha sido efectiva. BG: Sí, bueno la gente puede ver, hay alguna ayuda bien intencionada que no salió bien. Hay algunas inversiones de capital de riesgo bien intencionadas que no salieron bien. No deberíamos decir, está bien, gracias a eso, porque no tenemos un resultado perfecto, este es un mal proyecto. Debemos decir: ¿cuál era el objetivo? ¿Cómo tratamos de mejorar la nutrición, la supervivencia y la alfabetización para que estos países puedan cuidar de sí mismos? Y decir: ¡Vaya, esto va bien! Y ser más inteligentes. Podemos emplear la ayuda más inteligentemente. No todo es una panacea. Podemos hacerlo mejor que el capital de riesgo, en mi opinión, incluyendo grandes éxitos como este. CA: La sabiduría tradicional dice que es muy difícil para los matrimonios trabajar juntos. ¿Cómo lo han manejado Uds.? MG: Sí, me han dicho muchas mujeres: "Creo que no podría trabajar con mi marido. Simplemente no funcionaría". Saben, lo disfrutamos, y nosotros no... esta fundación ha sido un acercamiento para ambos en este aprendizaje continuo, y no viajamos tanto juntos para la fundación, como solíamos hacerlo cuando Bill trabajaba en Microsoft. Tenemos viajes a los que vamos por separado, pero siempre sé que cuando regreso a casa, Bill va a estar interesado en lo que aprendí, ya sea sobre las mujeres o las niñas o algo nuevo sobre el sistema de entrega de vacunas, o de esta persona que es un gran líder. Él va a escuchar y va a estar muy interesado. Y sabe que cuando él regresa a casa, incluso si es para hablar del discurso que dio o de datos o de lo que aprendió, que estoy muy interesada, y creo que tenemos una verdadera relación de colaboración. Pero no estamos todo el tiempo juntos, eso seguro. (Risas) CA: Pero ahora lo están, y estamos muy felices de que lo estén. Melinda, desde el principio, estuviste básicamente a cargo del programa. Hace 6 años, creo, Bill se integró tiempo completo, salió de Microsoft y se incorporó tiempo completo. Debió haber sido difícil, ajustarse a eso, ¿no? MG: Sí. Creo que en realidad, por parte de los empleados de la fundación, hubo mucha más angustia que de mi parte por la llegada de Bill. De hecho yo estaba muy entusiasmada. Es decir, Bill tomó esta decisión incluso obviamente antes de que fuera anunciada en 2006, y fue realmente su decisión, otra vez, fue durante unas vacaciones en la playa, cuando caminábamos por la playa y él empezaba a pensar en esta idea. Y, para mí, la emoción de Bill de poner su cerebro y su corazón al servicio de estos grandes problemas mundiales, estas injusticias, para mí era emocionante. Sí, los empleados de la fundación estaban angustiados por eso. (Aplausos) CA: Muy bien. MG: Pero eso desapareció después de 3 meses, una vez que él estuvo allí BG: Incluyendo a algunos de los empleados. MG: Eso fue lo que dije, los empleados, desapareció para ellos 3 meses después de que llegaste. BG: No, estoy bromeando. MG: Los empleados no se fueron. BG: Algunos de ellos se fueron, pero... (Risas) CA: Y ¿sobre qué discuten? Domingo, 11 en punto, no están en el trabajo, ¿qué surge? ¿Cuál es la discusión? BG: Como construimos esto juntos desde el principio, existe esta gran alianza. Tuve eso con Paul Allen en los primeros días de Microsoft. Lo tenía con Steve Ballmer cuando Microsoft se hacía más grande, y ahora Melinda, y aún de manera más fuerte, de igual manera, es la socia, así que hablamos mucho sobre: ¿a qué deberíamos darle prioridad? ¿Qué grupos están trabajando mejor? Ella tiene muchas ideas. Se sienta mucho con los empleados. Hacemos los viajes que describió. Hay mucha colaboración. No puedo pensar en algo en que uno de nosotros tuvo una opinión muy firme sobre una cosa u otra. CA: ¿Y qué hay de ti, Melinda? ¿Puedes? (Risas) Nunca se sabe. MG: Bueno, esto es lo que pasa. Nos aproximamos a las cosas desde diferentes ángulos, y de hecho pienso que eso es muy bueno. Así que Bill puede ver los grandes datos y decir: "Quiero actuar con base en estas estadísticas globales". Yo llego a ellas por intuición. Me reúno con mucha gente sobre el terreno y Bill me enseñó a confrontar esa realidad con los datos globales y ver si coinciden, y yo le he enseñado a tomar esos datos y reunirse con gente en el terreno para entender, ¿se puede en verdad entregar esa vacuna? ¿Se puede hacer que una mujer acepte esas vacunas contra la polio en la boca de su hijo? Porque la parte de entrega es tan importante como la ciencia. Así que pienso que ha sido más el acercarse con el tiempo hacia el punto de vista del otro, y, francamente, el trabajo es mejor gracias a eso. CA: En vacunas y polio y así sucesivamente, han tenido algunos éxitos sorprendentes. ¿Qué pasa con el fracaso? Pueden hablar sobre el fracaso y tal vez de lo que han aprendido de él. BG: Sí. Afortunadamente, podemos permitirnos algunos fracasos, porque ciertamente los hemos tenido. Trabajamos mucho con medicamentos y vacunas en los que sabes que vas a tener diferentes fallas. Por ejemplo, proyecto que tuvo mucha publicidad, requería un mejor condón. Tenemos cientos de ideas. Quizás algunas de ellas funcionaran. Fuimos muy ingenuos, ciertamente lo fui, con un medicamento para una enfermedad en la India, leishmaniasis visceral, que pensé, una vez que consiga este fármaco, podemos erradicar la enfermedad. Bueno, resulta que se necesitó una inyección diaria durante 10 días. Fueron necesarios 3 años más de lo que esperábamos, y luego no había manera de eliminarla. Afortunadamente, descubrimos que si matas a las moscas de la arena, probablemente tengas éxito. Pero pasamos 5 años, se puede decir que desperdiciamos 5 años, y cerca de USD 60 millones, en algo que resultó tener un beneficio muy modesto cuando lo conseguimos. CA: Gastan, cerca de, USD 1000 millones al año en educación, creo, algo así. La historia de lo que ha salido bien es un tanto larga y compleja. ¿Ha habido algunos fracasos que nos puedan contar? MG: Yo diría que una gran lección para nosotros es que pensamos que estas escuelas pequeñas eran la respuesta, y las escuelas pequeñas definitivamente ayudan. Reducen la tasa de deserción. Tienen menos violencia y crimen. Pero en ese trabajo aprendimos, que la pieza fundamental es un gran maestro en el aula. Si no tienes un maestro eficaz en el aula, no importa qué tan grande o pequeño sea el lugar, no se podrá cambiar la trayectoria de ese estudiante hacia la universidad. (Aplausos) CA: Melinda, esta eres tú y tu hija mayor, Jenn. Fue tomada hace solo 3 semanas, hace 3 o 4 semanas. ¿Dónde fue esto? MG: Fuimos a Tanzania. Jenn ha estado en Tanzania. Todos nuestros hijos han estado mucho en África. Hicimos algo muy diferente, que fue, que decidimos pasar 2 noches y 3 días con una familia. Anna y Sanare son los padres. Nos invitaron a ir y quedarnos en su boma. Incluso, las cabras estuvieron ahí, creo, viviendo en esa pequeña choza dentro su pequeño recinto antes de que llegáramos. Y nos quedamos con su familia, y verdaderamente aprendimos como es la vida en la Tanzania rural. Y la diferencia entre solo ir y visitar medio día o 3/4 de día a quedarse toda la noche fue grande, y te lo explicaré. Ellos tuvieron 6 hijos, y hablando con Anna en la cocina, cocinamos casi 5 horas ese día en la choza, y hablando con ella, ella había planeado y espaciado con su esposo los nacimientos de sus hijos. Era una relación muy amorosa. Eran un guerrero masái y su esposa, que decidieron casarse, claramente había respeto y amor en su relación. Sus hijos, sus 6 hijos, los 2 del medio eran gemelos, tenían 13 años, un niño, y una niña llamada Grace. Y cuando salimos a cortar madera y hacer todas las cosas que Grace y su madre hacían, Grace no era una niña, era una adolecente, pero no era adulta. Era muy, muy tímida. Quería hablar conmigo y con Jenn. Tratábamos de abordarla, pero era tímida. Aunque en la noche, cuando todas las luces se apagaron en la zona rural de Tanzania, y no había luna esa noche, la primera noche, y sin estrellas, y Jenn salió de nuestra choza con su pequeña lámpara para la cabeza, Grace salió de inmediato, tomó el traductor, fue directo hacia mi Jenn y dijo: "Cuando te vayas a casa ¿podrías dejarme tu lámpara para estudiar por las noches?". CA: ¡Vaya! MG: Y su padre me había dicho que tenía miedo que, a diferencia de su hijo, que había pasado sus exámenes de secundaria, por sus quehaceres, ella no hubiera salido tan bien y aún no estaba en la escuela pública. Él dijo: "No sé cómo voy a pagar su educación. No puedo pagar una escuela privada, y ella tal vez termine en esta granja como mi esposa". Así que ellos conocen la diferencia que la educación puede marcar de manera significativa. CA: Esta es otra foto de sus otros 2 hijos, Rory y Phoebe, junto a Paul Farmer. Criar a 3 niños siendo la familia más rica del mundo parece un experimento social sin precedentes. ¿Cómo lo han logrado? ¿Cuál ha sido su enfoque? BG: Bueno, yo diría que en general los niños reciben una gran educación, pero hay que asegurarse de que conozcan su propia capacidad y hacia dónde van, qué van a hacer. Nuestra filosofía ha sido ser muy claros con ellos; la mayor parte del dinero se va a la fundación y los ayudamos a encontrar algo que los apasione. Queremos lograr un equilibrio donde tengan la libertad de hacer cualquier cosa pero no colmarlos con mucho dinero para que terminen sin hacer nada. Hasta ahora, están muy aplicados, entusiasmados de abrirse su propio camino. CA: Han resguardado su privacidad cuidadosamente por razones obvias. Tengo curiosidad por saber por qué me han permitido mostrar esta fotografía aquí en TED. MG: Bueno, es interesante. A medida que crecen, saben muy bien que nuestra ideología familiar tiene base en la responsabilidad, que nos encontramos en una situación increíble solo por vivir en EE.UU. y tienen una gran educación, y tenemos la responsabilidad de devolverle al mundo. Así, a medida que crecen y les enseñamos, han visitado muchos países del mundo, dicen, queremos que las personas sepan que creemos en lo que están haciendo, mamá y papá, y está bien que nos muestren más. Así que tenemos su permiso para mostrar esta fotografía. Y creo que Paul Farmer probablemente va a ponerla eventualmente en alguno de sus trabajos. Pero realmente les importa profundamente, también, la misión de la fundación. CA: Tienen suficiente dinero a pesar de su enorme contribución a la fundación para convertirlos en multimillonarios. ¿Ese es su plan para ellos? BG: No. No. Ellos no tendrán nada de eso. Necesitan tener la sensación de que su propio trabajo es significativo e importante. Leímos un artículo hace mucho, en realidad antes de casarnos, donde Warren Buffett habló de eso, y estamos muy convencidos de que eso no le sirve ni a la sociedad, ni a los niños. CA: Hablando de Warren Buffett, sucedió algo verdaderamente asombroso en 2006, cuando de algún modo tu único verdadero rival para la persona más rica de EE.UU. de repente decidió donar el 80 % de su fortuna a tu fundación. ¿Cómo sucedió eso? Supongo que hay una versión larga y una versión corta. Tenemos tiempo para la versión corta. BG: Muy bien. Bueno, Warren era un amigo cercano, e iba a hacer que su esposa Suzie donara todo. Trágicamente, ella murió antes de que él se lo pidiera. Y él es bueno para delegar... (Risas) Él dijo... CA: Tuitea eso. BG: Si hay alguien que está haciendo algo bien, y está dispuesto a hacerlo sin cobrar, tal vez eso está bien. Pero estábamos sorprendidos. MG: Totalmente sorprendidos. BG: Nunca lo hubiéramos esperado, y ha sido increíble. Nos ha permitido incrementar nuestra ambición en lo que la fundación puede hacer, de manera espectacular. La mitad de los recursos que tenemos provienen de la alucinante generosidad de Warren. CA: Y creo que has prometido que para cuando te retires, el 95 % o más de tu fortuna, será donada a la fundación. BG: Sí. CA: Y ya que esta relación... si es increíble, (Aplausos) Y recientemente, Warren y tú han estado de un lado para otro tratando de persuadir a otros multimillonarios y a gente exitosa de que se comprometan a donar, más de la mitad de sus activos para la filantropía. ¿Cómo va eso? BG: Conseguimos cerca de 120 personas quienes ahora han asumido este compromiso de donar. Lo genial es que nos reunimos cada año y decimos: ¿Contratamos personal? ¿Qué les damos? No tratamos de homogeneizarlo. Digo, la belleza de la filantropía es esta diversidad asombrosa. La gente dona a ciertas cosas. Vemos y decimos: "Vaya". Pero eso es grandioso. Ese es el rol de la filantropía, elegir enfoques diferentes, integrados incluso en un solo espacio, como la educación. Necesitamos más experimentación. Pero ha sido maravilloso, conocer a estas personas, compartir su viaje a la filantropía, cómo involucran a sus hijos, lo están haciendo de forma diferente, y ha tenido mucho más éxito de lo que esperábamos. Ahora parece que va seguir creciendo en los próximos años. MG: Y que la gente vea que otras personas están logrando el cambio a través de la filantropía, es decir, estas son personas que han creado sus propios negocios, pusieron su propio ingenio detrás de ideas increíbles. Si pusieran sus ideas y su cerebro detrás de la filantropía, podrían cambiar el mundo. Y empezar a ver a otros haciendo esto, y decir: "Vaya, quiero hacer eso con mi propio dinero". Para mí, esa es la parte increíble. CA: Tengo la impresión de que es difícil para algunas personas entender cómo gastar tanto dinero en otros. Hay aquí probablemente algunos multimillonarios y seguramente algunas personas de éxito. Tengo curiosidad, ¿podrías vender la idea? ¿Cuál es la idea? BG: Es lo más gratificante que hemos hecho, y no te lo llevas contigo y si no es bueno para tus hijos, reunámonos a pensar ideas sobre lo que podemos hacer.
The world is a far better place because of the philanthropists of the past, and the U.S. tradition here, which is the strongest, is the envy of the world. And part of the reason I'm so optimistic is because I do think philanthropy is going to grow and take some of these things government's not just good at working on and discovering and shine some light in the right direction. CA: The world's got this terrible inequality, growing inequality problem that seems structural. It does seem to me that if more of your peers took the approach that you two have made, it would make a dent both in that problem and certainly in the perception of that problem. Is that a fair comment? BG: Oh yeah. If you take from the most wealthy and give to the least wealthy, it's good. It tries to balance out, and that's just. MG: But you change systems. In the U.S., we're trying to change the education system so it's just for everybody and it works for all students. That, to me, really changes the inequality balance. BG: That's the most important. (Applause) CA: Well, I really think that most people here and many millions around the world are just in awe of the trajectory your lives have taken and the spectacular degree to which you have shaped the future.
El mundo es un lugar mucho mejor gracias a los filántropos del pasado, y la tradición de EE.UU., es que lo más fuerte, es la envidia del mundo. Y parte de la razón por la que soy optimista es porque pienso que la filantropía va a crecer y tomará algunos de estos temas en los que el gobierno no es tan eficaz y arrojará algo de luz en la dirección correcta. CA: El mundo tiene una desigualdad terrible, un problema de desigualdad creciente que parece estructural. Me parece que si más de sus colegas siguieran el criterio que Uds. han tomado, tendría un impacto en ese problema y ciertamente en la percepción de ese problema. ¿Es un comentario justo? BG: Claro que sí. Si le quitas a los más ricos y le das a los menos ricos, es bueno. Se trata de equilibrar, y eso es justo. MG: Pero cambias los sistemas. En EE.UU., tratamos de cambiar el sistema educativo así que es justo para todos y funciona para todos los estudiantes. Eso, para mí, realmente cambia el balance de desigualdad. BG: Eso es lo más importante. (Aplausos) CA: Bueno, creo que la mayoría de las personas aquí y muchos millones en el mundo están impresionados por la trayectoria que sus vidas han tomado y el grado espectacular en que le han dado forma al futuro.
Thank you so much for coming to TED and for sharing with us and for all you do. BG: Thank you. MG: Thank you. (Applause) BG: Thank you. MG: Thank you very much. BG: All right, good job. (Applause)
Muchas gracias por venir a TED, por compartir con nosotros y por todo lo que hacen. BG: Gracias. MG: Gracias. (Aplausos) BG: Gracias. MG: Muchas gracias. BG: Bien, buen trabajo. (Aplausos)